<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Newrelic | code.eklund.io]]></title>
  <link href="http://code.eklund.io/blog/categories/newrelic/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code.eklund.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-18T11:35:55-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://code.eklund.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lukas Eklund]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Careful With Those Inflectors: A Tale of Performance Tuning Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://code.eklund.io/blog/2014/08/12/careful-with-those-infelectors/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-12T16:48:19-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code.eklund.io/blog/2014/08/12/careful-with-those-infelectors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We run our website at kaboom.org on a custom-built Rails 4-based CMS and for a long
time I was unhappy with performance of the site. Not that it wasn&rsquo;t responsive and
a huge (and I mean HUGE) improvement over the previous drupal mess, but requests
were spending more time than seemed necessary just in the ruby layer. Most requests were spending
almost 500ms there according to NewRelic traces.</p>

<p>I installed some tools locally to help track down where and why it was spending
so much time each request. The gem <a href="https://github.com/MiniProfiler/rack-mini-profiler">rack-mini-profiler</a> got me started and it is
a great way to get data on each and every request.
This helped me track down some code that was dynamically creating <code>store_accessors</code> for every request. There is an easy way to check if a
given <code>stored_attribute</code> exists on a class:</p>

<p><code>
Post.stored_attributes[:options].include?("some_attribute")
</code></p>

<p>Implementing this check and only adding the store_accessors when needed
provided a small performance increase but each request was still spending way
too much time in ruby. I spent some time trying to get usable data from
flamegraphs and also experimented with adding &lsquo;step&rsquo; blocks in my code to help
track down where things were slow. The problem I found with rack-mini-profiler
was that the rails stack is so deep it makes it very hard to see exacty where
the problems are. I still have it installed on a local branch that and I find
it very useful in some cases. But for this issue, it left me digging through a
convoluted flame graph and I decided to move on.</p>

<p>It was at this point I took a few weeks off from profiling and also took a
vacation. Several weeks later I was preparing for a bug day and was getting
error traces from New Relic to add to Trello that I revisited the performance
issues.  We are on Heroku so I decided to switch our free New Relic plan to the
plan the provides the paid-level features for a limited number of dynos. What
this gave me was access to my new favorite profiling tool: the New Relic thread
profiler. I ran the tool for a 5 minute trace and this was the result:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/blog/newrelicprof.png"></p>

<p>I had to uncollapse a few parts of the tree but it&rsquo;s pretty clear that the
request was spending over 56% of the time in the name method on the
ContentField model. Which, as it turns out, was a method that was no longer
even needed.
The offending, extraneous code:</p>

<p><code>ruby
def name
  return super if super.nil? || super.blank?
  super.downcase.parameterize.underscore
end
</code></p>

<p>I think this was added in the initial phases of building our CMS to ensure
conformity with seeded names alongside imported field names from Drupal. The
drupal importer I wrote handled all the transformations and there are
validations so enure that field names are created properly. This method does
nothing at all except run downcase, parameterize, and underscore on strings
that already conform to that format. And, as it turns out, <em>inflectors don&rsquo;t
come cheap</em>. I removed the method, ran my tests, and deployed a new version of
the CMS. The performance increase was noticable immediately:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/blog/transaction_performance.png"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not everyday that removing 4 lines of code (well, it was really just one) can give you such a boost in performance. Lessons learned:</p>

<ol>
<li>Careful with those inflectors! They can end up being performance bottlenecks.</li>
<li>Just because it was cached in memcache doesn&rsquo;t mean the object initialization doesn&rsquo;t incur the same cost.</li>
<li>NewRelic thread profiling is pretty awesome</li>
<li>rack-mini-profiler combined with flame graphs is an incredible tool that I need to spend more time learning how to use properly.</li>
<li>Careful with adding dynamic stored attributes with an after_initialize. They get added as class methods so only need to be added once.</li>
</ol>


<p>Helpful links:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://samsaffron.com/archive/2012/07/12/miniprofiler-ruby-edition">miniprofiler ruby edition</a></li>
<li><a href="http://samsaffron.com/archive/2013/03/19/flame-graphs-in-ruby-miniprofiler">Flame graphs in Ruby MiniProfiler</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.newrelic.com/docs/apm/applications-menu/events/thread-profiler-dashboard">New Relic Thread Profiler docs</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
